William Lloyd Imes Papers
William Lloyd Imes Papers
1881-1980
Imes, William Lloyd, 1889-1986.
14 linear ft.
Papers of the African-American clergyman. Correspondence, writings (including sermons by Imes and his father Benjamin A. Imes), memorabilia (including numerous small scrapbooks), and subject files.
149072
Biographical History
William Lloyd Imes (1889-1986) was an African-American clergyman, educator, and civil rights activist.
Imes was born December 29, 1889 in Memphis, Tennessee, to Benjamin A. Imes and his wife Elizabeth Wallace Imes. Dr. Imes received his B.A. degree from Fisk University in 1910 and an M.A. in 1912. In 1915 he received a B.D. from Union Theological Seminary and an M.A. from Columbia University. That same year he was ordained a minister in the Presbyterian Church and afterwards served as a pastor for Bethel Chapel, Plainfield, N.J. (1915-1919), Lombard Central Church, Philadelphia (1919-1925), and St. James' Church, New York City (1925-1943). He was awarded an honorary D.D. (Doctor of Divinity) from Lincoln University, Pennsylvania in 1929.
He entered the education field in 1943 when he became president of Knoxville College in Tennessee. Leaving there in 1947, he became Director of Social and Adult Education for the New York State Council of Churches, a position he held until his retirement in 1955. Following retirement, Dr. Imes traveled extensively as a lecturer and chapel speaker at many colleges and universities, and continued to be active in church affairs.
Dr. Imes was married in 1915 to Grace Virginia Frank, with whom he had three children: Wendell Phillips (deceased), Hope Mathilde, and Jane Elizabeth (deceased).
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The William Lloyd Imes Papers contain Correspondence, Writings, Memorabilia, and Subject files.
Correspondence is made up of both personal and public communiques and covers, with gaps, the years 1917-1980, with concentration in the 1960's. It is largely concerned with arrangements for speaking engagements at colleges and universities or in churches. The largest group of letters on a single subject runs from September 10, 1963 to October 7, 1965 and concerns the efforts of several members of the John Brown Monument and Historical Association to set up a Flame for Freedom at the John Brown farm at North Elba, N.Y. Leaders in this effort were Ernst L. Gayden, Clarence S. Gee, Boyd B. Stutler and Dr. Imes. Of note also is the letter written by Dr. Imes to the Nashville Banner on October 10, 1917, replying to a "scathing editorial" by that newspaper against Dr. Imes.
Writings, 1881-1970, contains addresses, book reviews, books, class and conference notes, lectures and notes, reports, research paper, and sermons. The class and conference notes are those taken by Dr. Imes as a student of various courses or as a participant at conferences. One of the interesting items in this group is a book of notes taken on lectures at Union Theological Seminary by such teachers as John Baillie, Eugene Lyman, and Harry Fosdick. The category of lectures and notes refers to lectures delivered by Dr. Imes, the largest number falling between 1940 and 1943 when he gave homiletics lectures at Howard University in Washington, D.C. The sermons form the bulk of the collection and, spanning the years 1914 to 1976, cover the full range of Dr. Imes's preaching career. Many sermons were delivered more than once, but they have been filed under the earliest date on the manuscript. Though many of the sermons are typescript, the greater part are holograph. Included in this section, at the beginning, is a group of sixteen sermons written by Dr. Imes's father Benjamin A. Imes. The writings reveal traditional religious and ethical themes but also a deep social interest on Dr. Imes's part. Civil rights for blacks and migrant workers is the topic of several addresses and sermons.
Memorabilia includes awards, church bulletins, clippings, a reproduction of the Declaration of Independence, and a large number of small daily diaries which Imes used as scrapbooks, filled with clippings and Imes' annotations.
Subject files contains material on a wide range of topics reflecting Imes' day to day work interests as a Presbyterian minister and an avid supporter of civil rights. Topics include John Brown, the NAACP, necrological records compiled by Dr. Imes for the Steuben-Elmira Presbytery, religion and race, and several folders of magazines, pamphlets, and newsletters collected by Dr. Imes and frequently containing annotations in his hand.
Arrangement of the Collection
The 1978 material and a few later additions were integrated with the rest of the collection in 2017. Correspondence is arranged chronologically. Writings are subdivided by type (addresses, articles, book reviews, books, etc.) and, within each type, arranged chtonologically. Memorbilia and Subject files are arranged alphabetically by type or topic.
Separated Material
Three items have been transferred to Rare Books for cataloging: The Black Pastures (1957) by Mr Imes, The Hills Beyond the Hills with chapters by Imes and others, and The Rev. J.W. Loguen, as a slave and as a freeman: a narrative of real life by Jermaine Loguen. Please refer to to locate these items.
Subject and Genre Headings
Church and clergy; African Americans; Imes, William Lloyd, 1889-1986.; Imes, Benjamin A.; Presbyterian Church -- Clergy.; Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.); African American clergy.; African American Presbyterians.; African Americans -- Biography.; Presbyterians -- United States.; Sermons, American.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Reviews (documents); Lecture notes.; Manuscripts for publication.; Newsletters.; Scrapbooks.; Sermons.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Dr. William Lloyd Imes, 1964-1980.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - [General], 1917-1957; 1962-1966; 7 folders (Box 1)
  - [General], 1967-1970; 5 folders (Box 2)
  - [General], 1971-1980; 6 folders (Box 3)
  - [General], undated (Box 4)
- Writings
  - Addresses, 1919-1964; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Articles
    - "The Black Pastures - An American Pilgrimage in Two Centuries, Essays and Sermons" (Box 4)
    - "Some Changeless Values of a Changing World" in The Southern Workman, Aug 1931 (Box 4)
  - Book reviews, 1929; 1939,; 1964,; 1969-1970 (Box 4)
  - Books
    - The Black Pastures, published edition, 1957; autographed; Transferred to Rare Books for cataloging. Please refer to to locate this item.
    - The Black Pastures, manuscript
      - Notes (Box 4)
      - Typescripts (Box 4)
      - Correspondence (Box 4)
    - The Hills Beyond the Hills, published edition, 1971; one chapter by Imes; inscribed by Imes to Syracuse University; Transferred to Rare Books for cataloging. Please refer to to locate this item.
  - Class and conference notes, 1927; 1935,; 1941,; 1950-1951,; 1953-1955 (Box 4)
  - Lectures and notes, 1938; 1940-1943 (Box 4)
  - Lectures and notes, 1962-1963 (Box 5)
  - Reports, 1936; 1951 (Box 5)
  - Research paper,"Dramatization as a Means of Control", 1916 (Box 5)
  - Sermons
    - Benjamin A. Imes, 1881-1905 (Box 5)
    - [General], 1914-1924; 11 folders (Box 5)
    - [General], 1925-1941; 16 folders (Box 6)
    - [General], 1942-1948; 7 folders (Box 7)
    - [General], 1949-1954; 6 folders (Box 8)
    - [General], 1955-1976; 3 folders (Box 9)
    - Undated sermons, notes, and fragments (Box 9)
- Memorabilia
  - Awards (Box 9)
  - Church bulletins, 1919-1959 (Box 9)
  - Church bulletins, 1960-1976; undated; 3 folders (Box 10)
  - Clippings (Oversize 1)
  - Clippings (Oversize 2)
  - Clippings (Oversize 3)
  - Declaration of independence, reproduction (Oversize 3)
  - Draft of report, "The Four Million", report of the New York State Citizens' Committee of One Hundred for Children and Youth, of which Imes was a member; 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Negatives (Box 10)
  - Programs, invitations, certificates, etc. (Box 10)
  - Scrapbooks, 1946; 1950; 2 volumes (Box 10)
  - Scrapbooks, 1951-1953; 4 volumes (Box 11)
  - Scrapbooks, 1953-1954; 5 folders (Box 12)
  - Scrapbooks, 1955-1956; 4 folders (Box 13)
  - Scrapbook, 1955; 1 volume (Oversize 4)
  - Scrapbooks, 1957-1959; 4 folders (Box 14)
  - Scrapbooks, 1960-1961; 4 folders (Box 15)
  - Scrapbooks, 1961-1964; 4 folders (Box 16)
  - Scrapbooks, 1965-1967; 4 folders (Box 17)
  - Scrapbooks, 1968-1969; 3 folders (Box 18)
  - Scrapbook pages, undated (Oversize 4)
  - Small address books, 1947-1958; 4 folders (Box 18)
- Subject files
  - John Brown (Box 18)
  - John Brown (cont.) (Box 19)
  - College bulletins, 2 folders (Box 19)
  - Jamaica, 1956 (Box 19)
  - Magazines and pamphlets (Box 19)
  - Magazines and pamphlets (Box 20)
  - Migrants (Box 20)
  - NAACP (Box 20)
  - Necrological records, 1963-1964 (Box 20)
  - New York State Citizens' Committee of One Hundred fpr Children and Youth (Box 20)
  - New York State Council of Churches (Box 20)
  - "News from NAACP", 1964-1965; printed newsletter (Box 20)
  - Presbytery of Geneva (Box 20)
  - Presbytery of Geneva (Box 21)
  - "Religion and Race Memo", 1964-1970; printed newsletter (Box 21)
  - Religious material, 3 folders (Box 21)
  - Union Theological Seminary (Box 21)
  - Union Theological Seminary, 3 folders (Box 22)
  - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 22)
  - Miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 23)